The origin of this circulatory system developing within these blood vascular islands
that are found in the duplication of my yolk sac.
This will have a speed that will later develop with my amniotic cavity
that will grow and the resorption, as well as the integration of the entire vascular system
inward.
We will see the emergence of a system known as the primitive aortic system
with the future heart that will develop and the system referred to as the veins.
A synonym is the mesonephric veins.
They will already play a very important role in the purification related to the first kidneys that will develop.
We increasingly see this integration of these vessels at the level
of the aortic system.
We see the importance of these vitelline veins, remember, which will form a whole
plexus here,
known as the plexus of the vitelline arteries that integrates here, of which the remnant
will later remain the mesenteric system that we will use.
Here we see the umbilical arteries
that will later merge here
and we will see here that we have
our digestive tube and we have what we call branchial arches.
You have the branchial arch that we call pharyngeal pouch number 1, number 2, number 3, number 4
up to 6.
Look, there are
one, two, three, four and then
actually there is one that appears but disappears very quickly.
We remove it in the literature, it has been described, we do not say 4, we do not say 5,
but we initially say 6.
What will be interesting to observe is the relationship of this whole vascular system that will change
and the main points to remember are that when we work at the level of the skull,
with the brain and this vascular system,
we must realize that we have this aortic arch coming from a lot of different segments.
It will be observed that the brain will be primarily vascularized by
Four vascular entry points, four things that I should check, four
things I can work with.
But remember that it is always a balance on the capillary beds, it is the exchange between
your arterial system and your venous system.
So these are energy transfer areas, it's a balance.
between what goes in and what goes out. You have the arterial system, venous, and then
the resulting effect with respect to my capillary beds will later give what we call the
lymphatic system. It is the perspiration that happens and creates an even more specific network
of cleansing. And so it is important that we have the area both
to irrigate and to disengage. And there we will see that
there is a continuity with the
vertebral plexus.
We talked about it yesterday. Each branchial arch will give a very specific arterial structure.
Branchial arch number 1, what is there? The remnant will be my maxillary artery.
But at the same time, regarding the skeletal derivatives, I have all this cartilage, but
it will have
all the derivatives down to the level of my inner ears. For children, this is very important.
They do not like it when we touch their skull. However, they do like it when we
go to their viscerocranium.
It is the brain that will form the skull.
While here, it is the surrounding space that will decide the formation
of the digestive tube.
Remember, there were lines of force that were established,
what we called in the form of dural sheaths.
And all these dural sheaths, anterior, middle, posterior,
were oriented towards my skull base.
And we saw that all my branchial arches were oriented towards this skull base,
which was this reference point, this support point.
both vascular, neurological, visceral, etc.
What is important is to create a balance at the posterior, middle, or anterior part.
I have the whole system of branchial arches number 1, maxillary artery,
I have the cartilage of my tortillas, and remember, I have all the stabilization for the tympanic cavity.
It is necessary to reconnect or allow this movement to rebalance towards its fulcrum, which is the base
of the skull.
And there, we will allow...
the space. Branchial arch number 1, the remnant, will give us what we call the
maxillary artery.
Then I have the second branchial arch which is what we call the hyoid system,
superior laryngeal,
inferior laryngeal, up to the thymic level. And thus I have the whole system that
organizes on my vascular plane. It organizes together. If
I take a skull, I will have
the dural sheaths coming to sit here, like
this, at my skull base, and all
my branchial arches, likewise.
This will be my reference point, you see, and everything organizes around that level.
This will be my neurocranium, this will be my viscerocranium, but
in my viscerocranium,
I find branchial arch number 1, where I will have the arch...
maxillary. For branchial arch number 2, I will have the stapedius artery and
the tympanic artery.
In the 3, I will come across the common carotid. In the 4, I will
come across
the aorta and the subclavians. And in the 5, there are none. And
in the 6, it will be pulmonary.
The whole system forms a functional unit with, for example, the laryngeal cartilages,
with the intrinsic muscles.
And among other things, with the recurrent branch of the vagus nerve.
I work with these units, I provide support points simply,
I let the lines of motility develop, the meeting of the neutrals,
and I let the space that contains the primary respiration,
thus allowing the emergence through the meeting of the two neutrals,
and the tide, the small tide or the great tide, can intervene.
Look at how the face has a vast vascularity.
Your face, even your bones, even your skin, even your cartilages, is from neural crest,
it's actually from mesoectoderm.
Not only do I have the support points that will be placed here, you see,
but before that, I have what I call the flow of the neural crest, prosencephalon,
mesencephalon, rhombencephalon, and then I have rhombencephalon 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. In this phase of
development,
this kind of flow, this invasion
of the neural crest over my ectoderms,
which is an important initial information.
Then I will have all the organization
in relation to my branchial arches
and in relation to my lines of force
always towards the same reference point,
which is a very important reference point,
which is my skull base.
So we saw that it corresponded
to the tip of the notochord.
At the arterial level, it gives movement.
It allows, on the hemostatic level,
a balance of volume.
and pressure, while the venous system is more of an exchange level,
more of an osmotic level,
immunity,
you see, everything related to the cerebrospinal fluid, that is the regulator, the controller,
it maintains
the specific molecular and hormonal balance of the body. And the return, always in
the law of the
venous system, with the choroid plexuses,
to produce the cerebrospinal fluid, the Pacchioni granulations for their resorption
and the lymph, I remind you, which returns to the system
with the grand plan of balance which are my capillary beds
that I remind you, is the place of encounter between the arterial and venous systems.
Each time at the level of capillary beds, an energy transformation,
a rebalancing of rhythmic zones, and a system of vasoregulation of the planes.
These are guardians of homeostatic balance on a fluidic level.
It corresponds to areas of copula too, specific rhythmic areas.
This is a rhythmic zone, this is a rhythmic zone, this is a rhythmic zone.